well hey and welcome back to heimlich's
history now in this video i'm going to
review everything you need to know about
unit 4 of the ap
u.s history curriculum and we ain't got
no time to waste so let's get to it now
before we get started i need to mention
that this review video is part of a
larger set of review materials that i've
made for you
the ultimate review packet for ap us
history it's got everything you need to
get an a in your class and a five on
your exam in may so if you're interested
link in the description below all right
so let's get down to reviewing unit four
the time period that we're covering is
1800 to 1848 and the main themes are as
follows first the expanding role of the
united states in world affairs
second the transformation of the society
and economy in the early years of the
republic and third we're going to see
how americans came to terms with all the
growing democratic impulses going on
during this time now we left off the
last unit with the election of thomas
jefferson in 1800 and now we're gonna
pick it right back up so you'll probably
recall that during this time there were
fierce debates between the democratic
republicans and the federalists on dang
near everything those debates just
continued right along into this period
two of the main debates being
about american relations with foreign
powers and the scope of federal power
back here at home so i reckon we ought
to look at both of them in turn now with
respect to america's relationship with
foreign powers a good example of the
debate during this period has to do with
the troublesome americans were having
with a group
of folks called the barbary pirates
since the 1970s the u.s government had
paid tribute to the barbary states of
north africa in exchange for their
protection of american merchant ships
and this was a policy put in place by
prior federalist presidents washington
and adams but our boy jefferson was
morally opposed to paying bribes in
order to engage in trade and so he
ordered those payments to cease so the
barbary pirates lifted their protection
and began attacking u.s merchant ships
and at this
jefferson sent the u.s navy to retaliate
but as things began to escalate towards
war
jefferson's administration negotiated a
reduced payment to the barbary states
and maybe even more divisive during this
time with the debates about the scope of
federal power back at home democratic
republicans as you may remember were all
about restriction of federal power and
that was the exact
opposite of the federalists the
democratic republicans championed a
strict constructionist view of the
constitution what this means is that
they believe that the federal government
was only able to do what was explicitly
written in the constitution now
federalists on the other hand were loose
constructionists this meant that the
federal government had a lot more
flexibility with the written word of the
constitution and therefore they could do
a lot more that wasn't explicitly
written in the constitution but as with
all things in history it's a little more
complicated than that case in point the
louisiana purchase
you might recall that france had a
colony in haiti and that starting in
1791 the haitians rose up in revolt
against the french and won their
independence in 1801 as a result of that
jefferson saw an opportunity to gain
navigation rights on the mississippi
river in new orleans which was squarely
in french territory
in north america and so we sent james
monroe over to france with two million
dollars in his pocket to secure those
rights from napoleon but now that haiti
was lost napoleon had little use for the
louisiana territory and so he went ahead
and told monroe that america could have
all of louisiana for 15 million
now monroe couldn't exactly call up
jefferson for advice so he went ahead
and took the deal now that seems great
and all but when monroe came home
heralding the good news that sent our
boy tj into kind of an existential
crisis remember he was a strict
constructionist and there is nothing in
the constitution that gives the power to
the president to buy land but there was
nothing he could do the deal was done
but jefferson justified the purchase to
himself by arguing that by owning the
new land indians could be removed
further westward and it would cut off
european influence in the region and
open up trading and bonus this land
would offer the potential to further his
agrarian dream for a nation of yeoman
farmers rather than the trade and
manufacturing nation that federalist
which is to say hamilton
envisioned so in this way jefferson who
is a strict constructionist actually
violated those principles and acted like
a common dirty federalist loose
constructionist now after the purchase
was complete congress appropriated funds
for a core of discovery led by
meriwether lewis and william clark lewis
and clark began the exploration of the
vast new territory beginning in 1804 and
they traveled thousands of miles up the
missouri river until they wound up on
the pacific coast the southern part of
the territory was explored and mapped by
zebulun pike in 1806 and the travels of
these two expeditions led to more
accurate mapping of the territory
greater geographic and scientific
knowledge of the region
and further diplomatic relations with
the indians who lived there now there
was further expansion of federal power
during this time and this happened as a
result of supreme court decisions and
for that we have our buddy chief justice
john marshall to thank and the first
case you need to know in this respect is
marbury versus madison in 1803. now it's
not that important that you know all the
details of this case but i'll tell you
the story just so you have some context
just before jefferson's election the
federalist dominated congress passed the
judiciary act which created 16 new spots
for federal
judges in the united states and on his
way out of office john adams appointed
federalist judges to fill
all those spots and one of those
appointments was to go to a judge named
william marbury i don't care how you
slice it that was a shrewd political
move because both the congress and the
presidency were changing over from
federalist to democratic republican
dominance
and this move was a way to ensure
continued federalist influence in the
courts now as it happened jefferson was
none too happy about this and so his
secretary of state james madison refused
to deliver some of those appointments so
the conflict wound
up in the supreme court and led by chief
justice john marshall the court decided
that under the judiciary act
marbury did in fact deserve his
commission well that's what i'm talking
about so that's the story but here comes
the sauce in this decision the court
also proclaimed itself
to be the final interpreter of the
constitution and that the judiciary act
itself was unconstitutional and the term
for this power is called judicial review
and therefore marbury would not receive
his commission wait
what so this had the effect of
increasing the power of the supreme
court and this increase in power just
continued in another case in 1819 called
mcculloch versus maryland and i won't
tell you the story here but just
understand that as a result of this case
the supreme court decided that federal
law
trumps state law okay so federal power
is increasing during this time but you
also need to understand that sometimes
regional interests took precedence over
national concerns and if you want an
example
and i know you do let's talk about the
war of 1812. now this is the first
proper war we've got ourselves into
since the revolutionary war so we need
to talk about the causes of this war so
during this time france and britain were
fighting because that's kind of their
thing the us wanted to remain neutral in
the conflict especially on the seas but
france and britain kept seizing american
merchant ships and that to put it mildly
was annoying additionally americans who
were moving westward were having indian
problems as was our custom and they
became convinced that the british were
stirring up this resistance finally
there was the problem of british
impressment and you might recall from
the last unit that the practice of
impressment just means that british
ships were forcibly capturing american
folks
and making them to serve in the royal
navy now this practice was hated but at
least understandable while america was
still a collection of british colonies
but now we got our big boy independence
pants on and the british were still
doing it so in june of 1812 the united
states declared war on britain and
support or resistance to this war fell
right along party lines the democratic
republicans were very much for it and
the federalists were very much against
in fact the federalists so opposed this
war that they met together at something
called the hartford convention in 1814
and amid their discussions about how to
end the war they even argued that as a
result of all this mess
new england should secede from the union
regardless america won that war and
there were some significant consequences
that attended it first the victory
created the occasion for an intense
nationalism in the american chess
after all here was the second war that
america had won against the mighty
british
i mean technically we didn't win it we
just kind of didn't lose it but you know
whatever the second consequence was the
final demise of the federalist party
because everyone was rejoicing in this
victory it seemed like the federalists
who were so staunchly opposed to this
war were so out of touch with american
reality and this marked the beginning of
a so-called era of good feelings with a
supposed national unity under the
democratic republican party however even
with the supposed national unity the
debates raged on the third consequence
is that even though the united states
won this war it did show us some of our
glaring weaknesses for example since
democratic republicans had let the
national bank charter expire in 1811
there was no national bank and therefore
was very difficult to raise funds
without a reliable source of credit
additionally without a reliable means of
infrastructure and transportation they
found it very difficult to move
men and supplies for the war effort and
the remedy to these problems gives us
another example of regional interest
trumping national concerns namely henry
clay's american system in this economic
prescription comprised of numerous
pieces of legislation and policies
three interdependent policies were
proposed with the intent of unifying the
american economy the first provision was
for federally funded internal
improvements like roads and canals that
would aid farmers and merchants the
second provision was for the
implementation of protective tariffs
tariffs by way of reminder are taxes on
imported goods and if you raise the
price on imported goods that has the
effect of making people want to buy
cheaper goods produced in america so the
tariffs would protect u.s manufacturers
and the third provision was for a second
bank of the united states now
president madison vetoed the first
provision for internal improvements
because he disliked
the way it would expand federal power
which he believed would disadvantage the
south but the other two provisions
passed now regional tensions were
further exacerbated by continued
westward expansion and a prime example
is when missouri applied for statehood
in 1819. settlers had already brought
thousands of enslaved people into the
missouri territory and so it was assumed
that missouri would come
in as a slave state but here's where i
tell you about the talmadge amendment
new york congressman james talmadge went
ahead and attached an amendment to
missouri's application for statehood
prohibiting slavery in the new state and
this was a massive
deal immediately it caused a firestorm
in congress and to understand why you
have to realize that of
utmost importance during this time was
to keep the balance in the senate
between free states and slave states if
missouri came
in as a free state that means that the
slave states would be the losers in the
senate on every vote that concerned such
matters
and so this little amendment threatened
to break up the union and even the word
civil war started to drip from people's
lips don't just take it from me let's
listen to our boy thomas jefferson he
said but this momentous question like a
fire bell in the night awakened and
filled me with terror
i considered it at once as the knell of
the union
it is hushed indeed for the moment but
this is a reprieve
only not a final sentence but our boy
henry clay stepped in to put a band-aid
on this gushing national neck wound he
proposed the compromise of 1820 also
known as the missouri compromise
according to this compromise they would
bring in missouri as a slave state and
then go ahead and bring in maine as a
free state and thus the free state slave
state balance in the senate would be
preserved and in order to solve the
problem for future expansion westward
they decided that the southern border of
missouri which is to say the 3630 line
would hereafter be
the line separating slave territory from
free territory
below it slavery would be permitted
above it not so much
except missouri of course okay so that's
what's happening back at home so now
let's turn our attention and look at
what's happening with america on the
world stage the major goals for america
during this period were to firm up our
boundaries and to gain more territory
and so in 1816 james monroe a democratic
republican
won the presidency he sent john quincy
adams over to london to settle some
territorial claims and adams negotiated
treaties that established the u.s
canadian border at the 49th parallel
and established joint u.s british
occupation of the oregon territory
okay now that we've got the north
squared away i know what you're thinking
was there a treaty that established the
southern border of the united states
there was i got you because monroe
wanted to limit the influence of spain
on the american continent he had old
john quincy adams negotiate the adams
onus treaty of 1819 as well in that
treaty spain went ahead and sold florida
to the united states and established the
location of our southern border and now
baby we're on a roll globally speaking
so let's keep going a couple of years
after these treaties were signed several
south american countries gained their
independence also from spain and monroe
seized this opportunity to proclaim
american dominance in the western
hemisphere in something called the
monroe doctrine of 1823 and basically
this doctrine just established the
western hemisphere as a u.s
sphere of influence perpetually to be
free
of european influence and if that
definition doesn't make any sense to you
think about it this way under the monroe
doctrine the united states is like a
giant dog lifting its leg and peeing all
over the western hemisphere uh hey y'all
this all belongs to me and you know that
cause i peed on it respect
all right so that's what's going on in
the wider world and now we need to turn
our attention to what's going on at home
in america during that time specifically
what's going on with our society and
what's going on with our economy and all
that could be summed up
with the market revolution so by
definition the market revolution was the
linking of northern industries with
western and southern farms which was
created by advances in agriculture
industry communication and
transportation and this is why henry
clay proposed the american system and
this had a massive
effect on america first of all new
technology gave this revolution its big
push forward the cotton gin and the
spinning machine revolutionized southern
agriculture and northern industry the
cotton gin significantly sped up the
process of separating seeds from cotton
fibers and the spinning machine sped up
the process of spinning cotton into yarn
and yet another technological
breakthrough that contributed to the
market revolution was the advent of
interchangeable parts
now prior to this generally speaking any
given product was made by artisans from
beginning to end but now in the midst of
the larger industrial revolution
machines were used to produce in bulk
the various parts of
say a musket and then assemble them all
together and this new process of
production became the basis for the
american system of manufacturing
basically you had water powered machines
the division of labor into small
repeatable tasks performed by unskilled
laborers
and therefore mass production also
steamboats transform trade now rivers
and streams have always been arteries
for trade but the problem with rivers
and streams is that they only flow in
one direction if you got a raft full of
goods to sell 100 miles downstream
that's great but baby you walking home
but now with steam power trading vessels
can navigate upriver and down river also
in this market revolution you had the
advancement of transportation the first
big leap forward came with the building
of canals for example the erie canal
that stretched across new york state now
in case you don't know what a canal is
it's just a waterway made by humans
sometimes rivers don't go where you want
them to go so you got to make one of
your own and once the economic benefits
of the erie canal were plain that
launched a huge campaign for more canals
to be dug all across the nation now by
the 1820s and the 1830s railroads began
to replace canals as the cinequa non of
transportation for trade and local and
state governments helped this process by
granting special loans and tax breaks to
railroad companies and the effect of all
this new technology is that american
industry became more interconnected and
interdependent than ever before and it
especially promoted the growth of
western agriculture now while all of
this was going on american society was
changing too
all across the north industrial cities
exploded in both population and
diversity for starters from 1820 to 1840
something like 2 million
immigrants showed up on the american
shores mainly from germany and ireland
and many of them settled on the eastern
seaboard and provided an expanding pool
of cheap labor which further fueled
northern industry others migrated west
and established homesteads and farms on
the frontier those immigrants who stayed
in the industrial cities transformed the
urban landscape they formed a growing
class of laboring poor and
as such they crowded themselves into
hastily built housing called tenements
and in these crowded tenements it was a
pretty bleak reality sanitation was an
afterthought diseases spread rapidly and
basically they lived there because that
was their only choice but even so many
of these immigrants were able to
re-establish their cultural institutions
that they had left back in their
homeland for example jewish immigrants
established synagogues and the influx of
irish catholics led to the expansion of
the catholic church and also there was a
growing middle class
this class first emerged in the north
and included folks like businessmen
shopkeepers journalists doctors and
lawyers with their growing prosperity
they had disposable income which they
spent on leisure activities like plays
and circuses and sporting events and hey
we got to talk about women during this
period too the ladies were expected to
conform to a developing societal norm
which was known as the cult of
domesticity and this was expounded
to them in a dizzying array of new
magazines and books that were being
published the idea was that a woman's
identity and sense of purpose revolved
around childbearing and making her home
a haven of rest for her husband the
husband's proper place was outside of
the home working and so this idea of
separate spheres for the sexes began to
really take hold in american society
during this time this is a middle class
and an upper class phenomenon and the
reason why it didn't extend to the lower
classes is probably obvious for the
lower classes the women had to work in
order for the family to survive
ain't no lower class woman got time to
sit around and make her husband's
sandwich all day all right now let's
take a hard right and talk about the
expansion of democracy during this time
to begin with it's going to be important
for you to know that the only people who
could vote during this time were
property owning white males so that
means that voting was the prerogative of
the elite but as the century progressed
working men and small farmers and
frontier settlers all began to demand
the franchise which is to save the right
to vote now in order to understand
why i need to tell you about the panic
of 1819 which was the first
major recession in united states history
the panic resulted from irresponsible
banking practices and a decrease in
demand for exported american goods
especially cotton now it was laboring
men who were hit hardest by this panic
and they wanted to be able to hold
politicians accountable for their
failures to regulate the banks but they
could not vote and this desire for the
franchise gathered more steam because
the frontier states had pretty much
all established universal male suffrage
and so by 1825
most eastern states had lowered or
eliminated their property qualifications
for voting and now that american
politics had an influx of new voters
that led to the growth and realignment
of political parties the election of
1824 led to a split in the democratic
republican party and the two factions
were as follows the group who called
themselves the national republicans had
a more expansive view of federal power
which is to say they were loose
constructionists in the lineage of old
school federalists and the group who
called themselves the democrats had a
restrictive view of federal power which
is to say they were strict
constructionists and with this rift
growing between them they had the worst
time nominating a candidate for the
presidential election and so they chose
four candidates
three of which will be important to name
there was andrew jackson who was a
democrat
in the jeffersonian mold there was john
quincy adams and then there was henry
clay who were both national republicans
with federalist tendencies now adams and
jackson were the strongest contenders
among the four but while adam stayed
home and let other people do his
campaigning for him
jackson went to the people and inspired
mass support so
jackson won the popular vote but because
there were so many candidates to choose
from
nobody won a majority of the electoral
vote in that case the constitution says
that it falls to the house of
representatives to choose the president
henry clay who came in fourth in this
contest who also happened to be the
speaker of the house through his support
behind adams
and the house chose adams to be the
president but not five seconds after
adams cheeks hit the chair in the oval
office he named henry
clay as his secretary of state and
jackson and all his supporters saw this
and cried
foul and they called it the corrupt
bargain but now fast forward to the next
election in 1828 and these intraparty
factions have actually crystallized into
legit political parties the democratic
party chose jackson as their candidate
and the national republicans went with
adams and jackson again took his
campaign across the country to all the
people and he ended up this time
winning the ticket and now we need to
talk about andrew jackson and his use of
federal power during his presidency by
the time he was elected the two major
national parties had shifted a little
bit the democrats were led by andrew
jackson and a new party called the whigs
was led by henry clay and the main
disagreement between these two parties
was basically this scope of federal
power and here's where i give you some
examples of this conflict and let's
start with tariffs specifically the
tariff of 1828. now this tariff was
actually passed during the adams
administration and it raised import
duties up to 50
as you can imagine northern
manufacturers and western farmers loved
this tariff because it protected their
industries but
southerners hated it because they relied
on imported goods and so now in 1832
under the jackson administration
congress went ahead and reaffirmed that
tariff and here's where things get a
little saucy i already told you that the
southerners hated the tariff in fact
they called it the tariff of
abominations
it just so happened that jackson's vice
president was a guy named john c
calhoun who happened to be a south
carolinian and calhoun shared the
southern hatred of this tariff and
developed the doctrine of nullification
and what this meant in practice was that
the states had the power to determine
the constitutionality of federal
laws and if a state found a law to fail
the test they could
nullify it or refuse to follow and so in
1832 when congress reaffirmed that
tariffs south carolina held a convention
and decided they would not pay those
taxes
and furthermore if federal authorities
came to collect those taxes south
carolina would secede from the union and
so andrew jackson not one to have his
authority flouted by a recalcitrant
state persuaded congress to pass the
force bill and the force bill gave
jackson the authority to use federal
troops to enforce federal law in south
carolina now jackson did work with
congress in order to lower the tariff so
that way south carolina could remain in
the union
and still save face but in a nasty
little thumb biting moment the south
carolina legislature went ahead and
nullified the force bill
so that's fun okay now a second
illustration over the divide of opinion
on the scope of federal power was
jackson's veto of the second bank of the
united states
now recall that this bank was
established as part of henry clay's
american system and it did stabilize the
economy throughout the 1820s but when
state banks started closing because they
couldn't make the required payments to
the national bank many people were left
with worthless paper money at that
jackson concluded that a national bank
favored the elite over ordinary citizens
and as a man of the people
he sought to correct that error and when
the recharter for the bill for the bank
passed congress and showed up on
jackson's desk he
vetoed it calling it a monster that was
dangerous to the common people of
america
and so the national bank was officially
dedsies and yet another illustration of
jackson's use of federal power was his
project of
indian removal now acquisition of indian
land was a big
issue before and during jackson's
administration and it came to a head in
the indian removal act of 1830 and there
are several different indian nations we
could look at here but let's just
consider the cherokee the cherokee
nation located in georgia had declared
itself a sovereign nation within the
borders of the state georgians however
did not see it that way to them the
cherokee were more like guests on their
land i mean y'all can chill on our land
that's all good
what there's golden in their hills oh
you all got to go
and so upon the passage of the indian
removal act the cherokee refused to be
resettled across the mississippi river
and they actually
challenged that law in the supreme court
in a case called worcester versus
georgia the court ruled that the
cherokee nation was in fact
sovereign and that georgia did not have
the right to impose state laws within
their boundaries and that was a great
win for the cherokee but then something
happened
in 1835 u.s officials persuaded a small
delegation of the cherokee to meet with
them and sign a treaty now this group of
cherokee did in no way have tribal
authority to do such a thing but
sign it they did the result was the
treaty of new ecota which officially
exchanged cherokee land in georgia for a
reservation territory west of the
mississippi river and for all who did
not relocate voluntarily the forced
removal began in 1838 along what became
known as the trail of tears
okay so that definitely happened but we
do need to move on and talk about the
distinct american culture and the spirit
of reform that was springing up during
this time it was very important for
americans to develop their own distinct
identity and in this period that largely
occurred through language philosophy
art and religion with respect to
american literature and language we need
to talk about noah webster in his
publication in 1828 of the american
dictionary of the english language
this dictionary was used in expanding
networks of schools and academies and
its chief effect was to standardize the
spelling and pronunciation of american
english because soon as far as i'm
concerned you ain't american unless you
speak america and we also got ourselves
a thoroughly american philosophy with
the advent of transcendentalism now i
say it was american but it was
definitely influenced by european
romanticism and its belief on human
perfectability additionally romanticism
in contradiction to the enlightenment's
emphasis on the thinking thinking parts
emphasized human passion
and mystery and so transcendentalism
followed all of this and
emphasized the transcendent power and
beauty of nature the first luminary of
this manner of thought was ralph waldo
emerson who believed that moral
perfection could be achieved in the
united states later a follow of
emerson's named henry david thoreau
moved to a cabin near walden pond
and he lived there among nature for a
year and made an experiment of human
perfection and all of his musings he
wrote down in a book called walden now
most of these folks supported other
moralist movements at the time including
abolition and temperance and women's
suffrage which is to say
there's lots of overlap throughout the
various reform movements during this
period and this manner of thinking also
influenced art
during this period for example the
hudson river school of artists painted
romanticized landscapes in new york and
the western territories and all of this
was an effort towards spiritual renewal
in america but some folks took this
desire for spiritual renewal even
further and created utopian communities
these groups of folks were usually very
influenced by european
intellectuals and american values of
democracy and equality and one of the
more famous of these groups was the
oneida community formed in 1848 in
central new york this group of
christians became convinced that the
second coming of christ had already
occurred and therefore they must shake
off the restraints of the kingdom of
this world and live communally and
imperfect equality and so each member
relinquished any private property they
owned and one of their more well-known
doctrines was that of complex
marriage and that is exactly what it
sounds like everyone
in the community belonged to everyone
else and so that means that the marriage
bed was
how shall i say this open but don't
worry the community was really big on
birth control methods you know like
jesus would have done when he
established his everlasting kingdom on
earth
anyway perhaps the most significant
spiritual renewal during this time was
the second
great awakening baptists and methodists
and presbyterians organized camp
meetings in the woods that folks
attended for days on
end and each day would feature up to a
dozen evangelical preachers who preached
with fervor all day long and it'll be
important for you to know that
in general these camp meetings were
relatively egalitarian which is to say
they included whites
blacks enslaved and free people men and
women but it wasn't all egalitarian
puppies and rainbows for example the
southern baptist went ahead and split
from their denomination because all
those cranky baptist abolitionists in
the north now this movement spread to
the cities chiefly by means of the great
preacher
charles finney finney was a new york
preacher who spoke powerfully in a
dialect and with images that common
folks could understand and they flocked
to hear him in droves and soon his
ministry of preaching spread across the
cities of the north and the flame was
lit for christian revival but in
contrast to the first great awakening
whose preachers focused intently on
personal
moral reformation finney and the
preachers that followed in his steps
were emphasizing the moral reformation
of society and it's important to mention
that because such messages set the stage
for the temperance movement which
crusaded against the consumption of
alcohol and going right along that line
in 1826 the american temperance society
was founded by
businessmen and clergy its efforts were
directed towards working-class men who
abused alcohol and the religious
revivals happening in the midst of the
second great awakening led to the
establishment of over 5
000 chapters of the ats across the
country and their goal was nothing less
than complete abstinence from alcohol
and the second great awakening also set
the stage for innovations on the
christian faith the most famous of which
being mormonism or the church of jesus
christ of latter-day saints
in the 1840s it was founded by a guy
named joseph smith who claimed to
receive visions from god at the age of
18. the substance of those visions was
pretty varied but the main idea is that
all churches in america had strayed from
the true teachings of the original
apostolic church and so being directed
to dig up some gold plates buried in the
hills of palmyra new york joseph smith
translated the plates into what became
their holy book the book of mormon now
in the beginning new yorkers tolerated
the mormon presence but once smith
proclaimed that god had instructed his
community to enjoy the institution of
polygamy
where men can marry many wives they fell
under persecution and so after smith was
lynched in missouri for such teachings
the next prophet of the group brigham
young
led the mormon community to establish a
theocracy on the great salt lake in the
utah territory okay still on the topic
of american society let's talk about the
growing movement of abolitionism in the
1820s the abolitionist movement was
mainly confined to free blacks and
quakers
but later in this period the movement
really started picking up steam one
cause for this was the publication in
1831 of william lloyd garrison's
newspaper the liberator he argued
forcefully that white folks needed to
take a stand against slavery by means of
moral persuasion and not violence in
1833 his cause had gathered enough
attention to create the american
anti-slavery society which spread
rapidly across the northern states but
you can't get the impression that
everyone in the north was an
abolitionist that's not how it was
northern merchants and manufacturers
actually feared abolition because of its
potential effects on the cotton and
sugar trade and on the other hand
white working men in the north felt
threatened by the prospect of abolition
because that meant their jobs could be
in peril now there were many women who
supported the cause of abolitionism but
they found that their status as women
made it impossible for them to advocate
for the cause as they wished and so they
concluded that in order to be more
effective in their campaigns they needed
more rights for themselves and so the
cause
of abolitionism and women's rights began
to grow up together out of the same sort
and to this end in 1848 women gathered
for the seneca falls convention in new
york this was the first women's rights
conference in america and there they
drafted the declaration of sentiments
which called for women's equality in
education
legal rights and voting and the fruit of
that movement won't come fully to bear
for a long time but this is where it
started and finally we need to talk
about a distinct subset of american
society during this time namely
the south after 1830 plantations began
to expand right along with westward
expansion when that happened plantation
owners profited enormously from their
expanded fields of sugar and cotton and
this created a wealthy plantation
aristocracy
which sought to protect their profits
and way of life through hard discipline
towards the enslaved people that worked
for them but even despite the harsh
conditions the enslaved laborers found
ways to keep their own sense of
community alive
one cultural aspect that's worth
mentioning is their songs
they sang songs that both created a
rhythm for their work and expressed
their collective despair
and also their collective hopes now
planters went to great lengths in order
to control their black laborers and one
of the reasons is that they were
perpetually haunted by the possibility
of slave uprisings and they had
good reason to fear because the haitian
revolution which was itself a slave
uprising wasn't that far in the past and
in 1831 their fears became a reality in
an event known as nat
turner's rebellion a black laborer named
nat turner organized a slave revolt in
virginia believing that god had given
him a mission to do so and by the end of
the rebellion he and his followers had
killed over 50 white people turner and
55 of his followers were hanged publicly
but this event only served to further
increase the fear among southerners of
more slave rebellions and so
out of that fear they imposed even
harsher disciplines
and restrictions on slaves now it's
going to be important for you to know
that most white southerners didn't own
any slaves at all they were yeoman
farmers which means they were
independent landowners but
it's important to know that even if they
owned no slaves they still believed in
general in the institution of slavery
and the racial hierarchy that made the
southern society work now as the soil in
the south became depleted of nutrients
because of over-farming
lots of southern farmers began moving
west and as a result of that slavery
began to grow in the west as well and
i'm sure that won't cause any problems
in the next period but we'll have to
wait till we get there to find out all
right i know that was a beast but that's
what you need to know about unit 4 of ap
u.s history if you want to go ahead and
grab the ultimate review packet go ahead
and click right here and all your dreams
will come true and if you want to join
the heimler family go ahead and
subscribe and let me know that you want
me to keep making these videos
i had a good time i hope you had a good
time heimler out